PhD, Computer Science
University of California, Santa Barbara

□ alonalbalak@gmail.com
□ Personal Webpage
□ GitHub in LinkedIn
■ Twitter Scholar

Alon Albalak

About Me

I am the Data Team Lead at SynthLabs, where we focus on research for post-training large foundation models. I received my Ph.D from the Computer Science Department at the University of California, Santa Barbara, while I was a member of the NLP Group, co-advised by William Yang Wang and Xifeng Yan.

The primary research focus of my research has been applying ML methods to NLP to improve data quality and model performance. In my research I have explored the use of methods including multi-armed bandits, data selection, multitask learning, transfer learning, reinforcement learning, and neuro-symbolic methods. Additionally, I have a wide array of interests in other topics including model efficiency, logic and reasoning, conversational AI, information retrieval, and multilingual models.

In the future, I am most interested in 2 main directions of work. First, I would like to continue my pursuit of data-centric research by understanding models from a data perspective, developing methods that improve data quality, and improving data efficiency. I am also very excited to apply my data-centric background to many areas of ML research, including model pretraining, alignment, fine-tuning, tool use, and neuro-symbolic systems.

Education

2018–2024 Ph.D, Computer Science, University of California, Santa Barbara.

UCSB NLP Group

Dissertation: Understanding and Improving Language Models Through a Data-Centric Lens

Advisors: William Yang Wang and Xifeng Yan

2016–2018 B.S., Mathematics, Wayne State University.

Selected Publications (Full publication list)

2024 Generative Reward Models.

Dakota Mahan*, Duy Van Phung*, Rafael Rafailov*, Chase Blagden, Nathan Lile, Louis Castricato, Jan-Philipp Fränken, Chelsea Finn, <u>Alon Albalak</u>*

Preprint

2024 DataComp-LM: In search of the next generation of training sets for language models.

Jeffrey Li*, Alex Fang*, Georgios Smyrnis*, Maor Ivgi*, ... Alon Albalak, ..., Achal Dave*, Ludwig Schmidt*, Vaishaal Shankar*

NeurIPS, Datasets and Benchmarks Track, Paper [Website] [Code]

2024 Generalization vs. Memorization: Tracing Language Models' Capabilities Back to Pretraining

Antonis Antoniades, Xinyi Wang, Yanai Elazar, Alfonso Amayuelas, <u>Alon Albalak,</u> Kexun Zhang, William Yang Wang

NeurIPS, Workshop on Attributing Model Behavior at Scale, Paper

- 2024 The Responsible Foundation Model Development Cheatsheet: A Review of Tools & Resources.

 Shayne Longpre, Stella Biderman, Alon Albalak, Gabriel Ilharco, Sayash Kapoor, Kevin Klyman, ...

 Preprint [Website]
- 2024 A Mathematical Framework, a Taxonomy of Modeling Paradigms, and a Suite of Learning Techniques for Neural-Symbolic Systems.

Charles Dickens, Connor Pryor, Changyu Gao, <u>Alon Albalak,</u> Eriq Augustine, William Wang, Stephen Wright, Lise Getoor

Preprint

2024 A Survey on Data Selection for Language Models.

Alon Albalak, Yanai Elazar, Sang Michael Xie, Shayne Longpre, Nathan Lambert, Xinyi Wang, Niklas Muennighoff, Bairu Hou, Liangming Pan, Haewon Jeong, Colin Raffel, Shiyu Chang, Tatsunori Hashimoto, William Yang Wang

TMLR, Transactions on Machine Learning Research, Paper [Github]

2024 Eagle and Finch: RWKV with Matrix-Valued States and Dynamic Recurrence.

Bo Peng*, Daniel Goldstein*, Quentin Anthony*, Alon Albalak, . . .

COLM, Conference on Language Modeling, Paper

2023 Improving Few-Shot Generalization by Exploring and Exploiting Auxiliary Data.

Alon Albalak, Colin Raffel, William Yang Wang

NeurIPS, Main Conference, Paper [code] [presentation]

2023 Efficient Online Data Mixing For Language Model Pre-Training.

Alon Albalak, Liangming Pan, Colin Raffel, William Yang Wang

NeurIPS, Workshop on Robustness of Few-shot and Zero-shot Learning in Foundation Models, Preprint

2023 RWKV: Reinventing RNNs for the Transformer Era.

Bo Peng*, Eric Alcaide*, Quentin Anthony*, Alon Albalak, ...

EMNLP, Findings, Paper [code]

2023 Logic-LM: Empowering Large Language Models with Symbolic Solvers for Faithful Logical Reasoning.

Liangming Pan, Alon Albalak, Xinyi Wang, William Yang Wang

EMNLP, Findings, Paper [code]

2023 CausalDialogue: Modeling Utterance-level Causality in Conversations.

Yi-Lin Tuan, <u>Alon Albalak</u>, Wenda Xu, Michael Saxon, Connor Pryor, Lise Getoor, William Yang Wang **ACL**, Findings, <u>Paper [code]</u>

2023 Addressing Issues of Cross-Linguality in Open-Retrieval Question Answering Systems For Emergent Domains.

Alon Albalak, Sharon Levy, William Yang Wang.

EACL, Demonstration Track. Paper [code]

2023 NeuPSL: Neural Probabilistic Soft Logic.

Connor Pryor, Charles Dickens, Eriq Augustine, Alon Albalak, William Wang, L. Getoor

IJCAI, Main Conference, Paper [code]

2022 FETA: A Benchmark for Few-Sample Task Transfer in Open-Domain Dialogue.

Alon Albalak, Yi-Lin Tuan, Pegah Jandaghi, Connor Pryor, Luke Yoffe, Deepak Ramachandran, Lise Getoor, Jay Pujara, William Yang Wang.

EMNLP, Main Conference. Paper [code]

2022 Making Something out of Nothing: Building Robust Task-oriented Dialogue Systems from Scratch.

Zekun Li, Hong Wang, <u>Alon Albalak</u>, Yingrui Yang, Jing Qian, Shiyang Li, Xifeng Yan **Alexa Prize Taskbot Challenge 2022**. Paper

2022 D-REX: Dialogue Relation Extraction with Explanations.

Alon Albalak, Varun Embar, Yi-Lin Tuan, Lise Getoor, William Yang Wang.

ACL, NLP for Conversational AI Workshop. Paper [code]

2021 Systems and methods for determining and using semantic relatedness to classify segments of text.

Rohit Jain, Devin H. Redmond, Richard B. Sutton, Alon Albalak, Sharon Huffner.

US Patent 11914963

2021 Modeling Disclosive Transparency in NLP Application Descriptions.

Michael Saxon, Sharon Levy, Alon Albalak, Xinyi Wang, William Yang Wang

EMNLP, Main Conference. Paper

Professional Experience

April 2024 - Data Team Lead, SynthLabs.

present o Directed the internal research agenda on synthetic data generation, data filtering, and reward models

- o Developed and led open-science collaborations with the broader research community
- o Resulting Publications: Generative Reward Models

June 2022 – Research Science Intern, Meta Al.

September o Directed and executed on 2 projects in collaboration with researchers across the company

2022 • Explored data-efficiency through the use of multi-task learning and various prompting methods for small language models

- o Explored the use of parameter-efficient methods for zero-shot generalization
- o Resulting Publications: Data-Efficiency with a Single GPU

June 2019 – Research Associate, Theta Lake.

2020

- September o Built classifiers for automated risk detection in regulated industries through the use of natural language processing and other machine learning techniques
 - o Took multiple projects from inception to production, and developed 2 patent pending methods along
 - o Resulting Patent: US Patent 11914963

Fellowships & Awards

- 2023 Neurips Scholar Award, 37th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems.
- 2018 Integrative Graduate Education and Research Traineeship (IGERT) Fellow, University of California, Santa Barbara.
- 2018 Academic Excellence Fellowship, University of California, Santa Barbara.
- 2018 Chia Kuei Tsao Award, Wayne State University. For outstanding academic achievement in the undergraduate mathematics program

Service & Outreach

- ACL 2023-24 Workshop Organizer NLP For Conversational AI (NLP4ConvAI)
 - ACL 2023 Social Organizer Mindfulness meditation in a time of NLP hyperactivity
- NeurIPS 2022 Workshop Organizer Transfer Learning for NLP (TL4NLP): Insights and Advances on Positive and Negative Transfer. Proceedings.
 - 2022-2024 Program Committee: ACL, NAACL, EMNLP, AAAI

Technical skills

Tools Python, C++, Shell, AWS, Azure

Packages PyTorch, TensorFlow, HuggingFace, NumPy, SciPy

Machine Natural language processing (NLP), computer vision (CV), transformers, generative AI, statistical

Learning analysis, regression, clustering

Military Experience

2012 – 2015 Reconnaissance Sabotage Unit, Israel Defense Forces.

- o Engineering, demolitions, and reconnaissance specialty training
- o Battalion lead navigator